<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-13T15:42:29+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Saranga Sudarshan</title><entry><title type="html">Women’s Soccer and Structural Injustice</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/philosophy/2015/10/29/WomensSoccerStructuralInjustice.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Women’s Soccer and Structural Injustice" /><published>2015-10-29T00:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2015-10-29T00:00:00+11:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/philosophy/2015/10/29/WomensSoccerStructuralInjustice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/philosophy/2015/10/29/WomensSoccerStructuralInjustice.html">&lt;p&gt;A little over a month ago the Australian Women’s National Football team, the “Matildas”, went on strike over a wage and conditions dispute with the Football Federation of Australia (FFA). It seemed astounding that an Australian sporting team, in 2015, was being paid below the minimum wage and yet perform at the level of professional athletes. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/football/2015/sep/11/matildas-player-strike-what-are-the-key-pay-demands-and-disputes-ahead&quot;&gt;Commentary&lt;/a&gt; in the media seemed, as it so often does, to focus on a few narrow issues. Whilst the issues were not superficial, they did not really reach the fundamental nature of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.smh.com.au/sport/soccer/ffa-gives-the-matildas-historic-chance-to-become-professional-athletes-and-raises-aleague-salary-cap-20150929-gjxhpd.html&quot;&gt;commentators&lt;/a&gt; were, quite rightly, surprised that the Matildas pay and working conditions paled in comparison to the men’s team. How could professional athletes be expected to train several times a week, go on long tours to foreign countries and yet not be paid a liveable wage? The difference in payment between the Matildas and the Socceroos is hard to ignore yet unsurprising. The women’s game probably, and I have not been able to get hard figures, raises less revenue than the men’s game. There is less money to go around. This seems a safe inference to make, putting aside any perfectly valid arguments about the efficient use of the available revenues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.abc.net.au/radionational/programs/backgroundbriefing/inside-the-matildas-strike/6837756&quot;&gt;argument&lt;/a&gt; in the commentariat has been the one from desert. The Matildas deserve better pay simply because they perform better than their male counterparts. They win more games, more tournaments and as such are more competitive. It seems when viewed as a pure workplace issue, the Matildas are being underpaid for overperforming. Once again, there is little that can be said in response. Perhaps one can return to the earlier response that with less revenue available, either through sponsorships and broadcasting rights, the Matildas should be paid less than the Socceroos because they raise less revenue for the FFA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I believe the fundamental problem is that we tend to ignore the affect of social behaviours and what the philosopher Iris Marion Young calls “structural injustice”. This problem is ignored because we ignore the private enterprise nature of professional sports in Australia. Professional athletes operate in a open marketplace just like any other worker. And so the fundamental question to ask is why the Matildas have such poor conditions in a free labour market? There is no inequality in law or otherwise in the freedom of female soccer players to pursue their athletic careers or any other career. There is no inequality in opportunity for female soccer players either. They have the same chance as any other woman or man to either play soccer at a professional level or pursue other more gainful work. The injustice that jumps out at us is more subtle and so less discussed. Nevertheless to my mind the diagnosis is simple, it is what Young called “structural injustice”, or injustice outside the framework of our basic social institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Matildas, much like other work primarily done by women, has historically been valued less than men’s work. No doubt our values have changed and this is increasingly become less true, but the Matildas’s circumstance highlights an acute case where Young’s phenomenon of structural injustice is clearly on display yet altogether ignored. The Matildas have poor working conditions precisely because the social behaviours that dictate the fluctuations in the labour market, the advertising market and consumer goods markets value the men’s game more than the women’s game. The important point to notice here is that the Matildas are not being discriminated against by any one individual or any one institution. They are affected by the network of behaviours we exhibit. We choose to ignore women’s sport, the little that is broadcast, and we choose to put less money behind our purchase of goods that women exclusively might use, which would be prime candidates for advertising during women’s soccer matches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we accept this analysis the challenge that presents itself is to work out the just way to redress the injustice. There seems no clear liberal answer to such a problem. It seems illiberal to coercively change what people value. One approach to a solution, that I will not fully argue for here, is that we should look more closely at how our institutional arrangements hold us responsible for the choices we make. Perhaps we should be held responsible, either in practical measures, or in argument, for valuing men playing sport more than women playing sport. At the very least this would require a broader understanding of how women cannot always choose the choices open to them in liberal societies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="philosophy" /><summary type="html">A little over a month ago the Australian Women’s National Football team, the “Matildas”, went on strike over a wage and conditions dispute with the Football Federation of Australia (FFA). It seemed astounding that an Australian sporting team, in 2015, was being paid below the minimum wage and yet perform at the level of professional athletes. Commentary in the media seemed, as it so often does, to focus on a few narrow issues. Whilst the issues were not superficial, they did not really reach the fundamental nature of the problem.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Normative Challenge Against Destiny</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/philosophy/2013/02/07/ANormativeChallangeAgainstDestiny.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Normative Challenge Against Destiny" /><published>2013-02-07T00:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2013-02-07T00:00:00+11:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/philosophy/2013/02/07/ANormativeChallangeAgainstDestiny</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/philosophy/2013/02/07/ANormativeChallangeAgainstDestiny.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DSC_0089800.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;profile&quot; style=&quot;float:left;margin:0px 15px 15px 0px;width:20%;height:auto;&quot; /&gt; Something that I’m noticing more and more every time I visit India are the problems caused by what my relatives call “Karma”. Karma there is not used in common parlance the same way a theologian might use, but it is a general term referring to someone’s destiny. The destiny in question is metaphysical such that it exists not as a proverb but as a real feature of reality. By this I mean that destiny or someone’s destiny is not just an idea or a theory about something, it is a feature of reality. I think there is a good argument to be made that we should not believe that destiny is real if we want an egalitarian, law abiding society. Let me be clear this is not an argument about whether destiny is actually a feature of reality, but whether we should believe that it is if we want our society to be egalitarian and generally law abiding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off let me make myself precise. When someone believes in destiny, it could mean one of two things. (1) They believe at any present moment, that their future is fixed and unchangeable, but that they will be the cause of that future no matter what. (2) They believe that their future is fixed and that no matter what they do between the present and any future time, that future will come about no matter what. It is the second type of belief that I am concerned about. It is a belief that what will happen in a future time is already fixed and that whatever one does between the present and that future time it is of no use. In all of this I take “fixed” or “metaphysically fixed” to mean that a future event will metaphysically necessarily occur. I do not make any claims as to whether these future events exist now or only in some objective present. All that “fixed” is meant to convey is the metaphysical necessity of an event occurring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is belief (2) I think that prevents a society from being egalitarian and law abiding. Of course no society is perfectly egalitarian or law abiding, but generally tries to balance the egalitarian value of equality with the liberal value of liberty. It is this balance that most liberal egalitarian democracies attempt to strike and an attempt that they believe makes them good societies. Nevertheless I will only be  concerned with the effect that a belief in destiny has on the inequality of basic rights and socio-economic opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an individual believes that destiny is real they believe that each and every person has fixed future events that they will be a part of no matter the causal connection between the person’s present actions and future actions. How does this belief prevent a society from being egalitarian? Well because it explains past, present and future inequalities of basic rights and opportunities in society as fixed types of states of affairs that cannot and could not be metaphysically different. By “types of states of affairs” I mean something like “Sheila falling ill”. This type of state of affairs is different from a specific “state of affairs” like “Sheila falling ill from the unmaintained sewage pipes that leak sewage into drinking water”. Sheila falling ill is a type of state of affairs that could be instantiated in many different ways. I am making this clear because I do not believe that individuals who believe in their destiny believe there are no causal connections between specific states of affairs, but just that there are no causal connections between types of states of affairs  This means individuals cannot be held responsible for situations where individuals have unequal access to basic human rights because the types of states of affairs of a society at any given time could not have been different no matter the actions of the individuals. Therefore individuals have no causal powers to bring about future types of states of affairs. While they do have causal connections and are the cause of states of affairs like eating cereal instead of toast, they just don’t believe they have a causal connection or causal powers to influence whether they have breakfast or not. In this case “having breakfast” is a type of state of affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I should make it clear what counts as a type of state of affairs and what counts as a specific state of affairs. What counts as a state of affairs is an object that has certain properties at a certain time. An object here can be anything from an atom to a human being. And I am using properties in a very restricted sense. Properties are just the sparse physical features, such as an exact mass or an exact spatio-temporal location. A type of state of affairs is just the same thing without a specific object to which the properties are attached. “Something or someone having the property of carrying a Tuberculosis causing bacteria” is a type of state of affairs. This is not to say again that it is uncontroversial that states of affairs and types of states of affairs exist. It is just that it provides a way of making sense of what an individual believes about the world when they believe that destiny is a real feature of that world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If individuals have no causal powers to bring about types of states of affairs then they cannot be held morally responsible for a causal link they have to future inequalities because that future unequal type of state of affairs is metaphysically fixed and unchangeable. By unequal states of affairs I just mean states of affairs where two individuals have an unequal access to socio-economic opportunities or their basic rights. The poor labourer, let us call her Sheila was always going to be a poor labourer not because society discriminates against her for being of a certain sex, gender, religion or race, but because it is metaphysically fixed and unchangeable that she was to be a poor labourer. This, while not a necessary explanation of Sheila’s situation from a belief in destiny, is a consistent explanation of Sheila’s situation. This explanation permits serious inequalities in society. The wealthy landlord, let us call him David, has no reason to treat Sheila as he would treat his friends namely in a non-discriminatory manner, because his and Sheila’s socio-economic status could not have been different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us consider an example where the specific states of affairs are different. Sheila may have had the same socio-economic status as before, but now she is a disabled beggar and David is a middle class professional. It is the types of states of affairs, namely the socio-economic positions in an absolute or relative sense that could not have been different. So the contention is that the types of states of affairs, namely the socio-economic status of Sheila and David are the same in our second example as they were in the first example. In fact David can justify any future discrimination against Sheila as an unchangeable type of state of affairs that is metaphysically fixed such that even if he locks himself in a room Sheila will be discriminated against somehow by someone. As soon  as arbitrary discrimination against individuals is justified and accepted by a society it ceases to be egalitarian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course there is no real danger in a society ceasing to be egalitarian if only one or two individuals firmly believe in destiny, but it is dangerous when the majority in a society believe it. There is no rational reason to change or alter inequalities in society if a society believes that everyone and everything has a destiny. There is no point in people organising democratically because they can only be the cause of states of affairs instantiating fixed types of states of affairs. Since individuals have no causal links to types of states of affairs they cannot change future occurrences and so they need not bother trying to change something they metaphysically cannot change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DSC_0091800.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;profile&quot; style=&quot;float:right;margin:0px 0px 15px 15px;width:35%;height:auto;&quot; /&gt; Now how does a belief in destiny make a society less law abiding? Well because law breaking itself is seen as a type of state of affairs, while “stealing a car” is a specific state of affairs instantiating law breaking. If law breaking is a type of state of affairs then individuals have no causal link to its occurrence because it is fixed whether it will occur or not. It is however not fixed and changeable by whom or what it will be instantiated by. It could be said that individuals would not break laws once they saw the punishment society gave for law breaking. A belief in destiny, at least in the way I have dealt with it, would override this deterrent because the act of law breaking and the punishment received is seen as a type of state of affairs that cannot be changed. While it is not fixed by any means how exactly this type of state of affairs will be instantiated  it is fixed that someone, some how will break the law. Even the punishment received is a type of state of affairs because it is fixed whether the law breaker will be caught or not, and whether they will be punished. It is not fixed in what specific way they will be caught and punished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if a society wants to be an egalitarian and law abiding society then I think there is good reason for the individuals in that society not to believe that destiny is real. None of this is to say whether destiny is real or whether equality or law abiding citizens are things that society should be promoting. Society could well be focused just on increasing the liberty of individuals and do nothing for the inequality of  individuals accessing their basic rights or socio-economic opportunities. If this was the case there could potentially be no undesirable consequences with a belief in destiny.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="philosophy" /><summary type="html">Something that I’m noticing more and more every time I visit India are the problems caused by what my relatives call “Karma”. Karma there is not used in common parlance the same way a theologian might use, but it is a general term referring to someone’s destiny. The destiny in question is metaphysical such that it exists not as a proverb but as a real feature of reality. By this I mean that destiny or someone’s destiny is not just an idea or a theory about something, it is a feature of reality. I think there is a good argument to be made that we should not believe that destiny is real if we want an egalitarian, law abiding society. Let me be clear this is not an argument about whether destiny is actually a feature of reality, but whether we should believe that it is if we want our society to be egalitarian and generally law abiding.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Amour</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/movies/2013/01/26/OnAmour.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Amour" /><published>2013-01-26T00:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2013-01-26T00:00:00+11:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/movies/2013/01/26/OnAmour</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/movies/2013/01/26/OnAmour.html">&lt;p&gt;Michael Haneke’s, Amour, is unequivocally a masterpiece of modern cinema and most definitely one of the best films of 2012. The narrative is both clear and yet cinematically dense. Two things that are often difficult to produce on screen. The performances, particularly of the two leads, Emmanuelle Riva and Jean-Louis Trintignant, are realistic, subtle and seemingly effortless. Both performances communicate in volumes about the characters. The sound design is used not just for loud effects but to mark returning metaphors seamlessly. This post does does contain some spoilers about the climax in the film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/haneke2009.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;profile&quot; style=&quot;float:left;margin:0px 15px 15px 0px;width:20%;height: auto;&quot; /&gt; Haneke begins with Anne and Georges in their happy twilight years, enjoying their passion - music. The narrative begins its work from here, by marking Anne as a fiercely independent woman. It is into this retired bliss that Anne’s stroke leads to her being paralysed on one side of her body and dependent on Georges. The narrative from that point on is woven with sudden and crisp flashes of Georges imagination and memories of his once healthy vibrant wife. Almost every scene deals with the way relationships of love become almost too cruel to bear in the wake of inevitable death. A masterful scene is the seamless dream sequence in which Georges’s weariness, suffocation and sadness from caring for his wife are shown. The sequence works because Haneke has already marked early in the film the possibility of a robbery in the apartment. It is this latent fear that Haneke uses to heighten Georges’s nightmare as a metaphor for his current anguish. Another masterful scene is the one after which Georges kills his wife where he catches a pidgeon. The scene again works as cinematic moment because we expect Georges to kill the pidgeon since we have been shown his chasing a pidgeon out of the apartment earlier and we expect his violence to carry on. Presenting Georges simply petting the pidgeon cinematically develops the metaphor of his character as inherently non-violent and that he has euthanised his wife rather than murdered her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emmanuelle Riva’s performance is outstanding in its detail and cinematic efficacy. Her slow degradation into complete paralysis and death is unnoticeable. Jean-Louis Trintignant, portrays the weariness and heartache of watching a loved one decay. He affects a limp suggesting that before his wife’s stroke he was the one expected to fall ill and that he is no way fit to be a full time carer. It is a testament to Haneke’s courage that he chooses not to explain but lets the performances communicate cinematically rather than as exposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sound design is definitely a case of less is more - much much more. The absence of non-diagetic music throughout the film is in itself a cinematic metaphor. Apart from the fact that absence music gives us no respite from the narrative, it also works on showing Georges and Anne are not living with their passion. They are accomplished music teachers who have the harsh reality of death forced upon them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is reality that eventually consumes this film in the last scenes where Anne and Georges’s daughter Eva walks around the empty flat. It is the ugly reality of helplessness, lonliness and the absence for what we want most in a world that doesn’t stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saranga Sudarshan&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(photo by Georges Biard courtesy of creative commons)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="movies" /><summary type="html">Michael Haneke’s, Amour, is unequivocally a masterpiece of modern cinema and most definitely one of the best films of 2012. The narrative is both clear and yet cinematically dense. Two things that are often difficult to produce on screen. The performances, particularly of the two leads, Emmanuelle Riva and Jean-Louis Trintignant, are realistic, subtle and seemingly effortless. Both performances communicate in volumes about the characters. The sound design is used not just for loud effects but to mark returning metaphors seamlessly. This post does does contain some spoilers about the climax in the film.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Koormavatara</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/movies/2013/01/19/OnKoormavatara.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Koormavatara" /><published>2013-01-19T00:00:00+11:00</published><updated>2013-01-19T00:00:00+11:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/movies/2013/01/19/OnKoormavatara</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/movies/2013/01/19/OnKoormavatara.html">&lt;p&gt;Koormavatara, by Girish Kasaravalli, as I saw it recently at Bangalore International Film Festival, was at once a forceful narrative but also a wandering film with an unsuccessful climax. The emotionally withdrawn Anand Rao’s journey of, at first reluctantly, playing Gandhi in a TV drama is the central device through which Kasaravalli explores the trouble of authenticity in historical perception and historical portrayal in art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/kasaravalli.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;profile&quot; style=&quot;float:left;margin:0px 15px 15px 0px;width:20%;height: auto;&quot; /&gt; Rao’s portrayal of Gandhi finds him in conflict with his director. It is this conflict between Rao’s insistence on a historically accurate portrayal as opposed to the directors cinematic or more emotional portrayal that brings to the fore the tension between two ways of representing history. Particularly the scenes early in the film show the cinematic representation to be more authentic then Rao’s perception. Despite this later scenes show that the subjective portrayal of Gandhi is as authentic and accurate as the researched cinematic version. This slowly changing relationship between Rao and his director shows a subtle metaphor about how both ways of representing history are plagued by subjectivity and that Rao’s representation informs the director’s and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film nevertheless is not without its shortcomings. All the performances are engaging and well rounded although Shikarapura Krishnamurthy who plays Rao is flat at times. The return to a stock selection of emotional states and gestures causes some scenes such as those where Rao argues with the director, played by Apoorva Kasaravalli, to lose their poignancy. With this are some unnecessary plot points, especially that of Rao’s sudden repenting for not caring for his late wife who died of cancer. This sudden repentance seems both out of character and contributing little to the narrative. The continued reappearance of the tortoise motif seems to go no where or at least seems to lack efficacy in communicating what it sets out to communicate. Perhaps the film’s biggest shortcoming is its climax. The climatic sequences where Rao refuses to help his son out debt and also fails to stand up for his friend’s son, Iqbal are illogical and overbearing respectively. Rao’s sudden refusal to help his son because he has a quasi-moral objection to share-trading is inconsistent if not unbelievable. Rao’s failure to stand up for Iqbal, played by Vikram Soori, who is removed from the role of Godse because he is a muslim is too loud a metaphor about religion and communalism in an otherwise subtle film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Koormavatara then is a film that is definitely worth watching for its meta-discussion about art and history, but is also definitely not one of Kasaravalli’s best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saranga Sudarshan&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(photo by Hari Prasad Nadig)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="movies" /><summary type="html">Koormavatara, by Girish Kasaravalli, as I saw it recently at Bangalore International Film Festival, was at once a forceful narrative but also a wandering film with an unsuccessful climax. The emotionally withdrawn Anand Rao’s journey of, at first reluctantly, playing Gandhi in a TV drama is the central device through which Kasaravalli explores the trouble of authenticity in historical perception and historical portrayal in art.</summary></entry></feed>